Finding Aid for the Donald F. McCallum papers LSC.2318
UCLA Library Special Collections
Donald F. McCallum papers
1968-2013
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2318
4.2 Linear Feet (10 boxes, 1 half box, and 11 unprocessed CDs)
Donald F. McCallum was an art historian, professor, and chair at UCLA's Department of Art History. Born in Vancouver, British Columbia on May 23, 1939, he earned his AB at UC Berkeley (1962), and his PhD at the Institute of Fine Arts, New York University (1973). He was a scholar of Japanese art history and spent seven years doing research and fieldwork in Japan. McCallum's research on Japanese art is focused on Japanese Buddhist art and sculpture, as well as Korean influences on Japanese art. This collection includes materials related to his academic career and research, course materials, lecture notes, papers, correspondence, and presentations. Topics covered in this collection include Korean and Japanese art history, Korean Buddhism, Silla-period sculpture, Sui styles, the Tachibana Shrine, Japanese sculpture and architecture, and the Fujiwara-kyo Palace. He passed away on October 23, 2013 at the age of 74.
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE: Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Toshiko McCallum; Gift; 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8564813
Biographical / Historical
Donald F. McCallum was an art historian and professor at UCLA's Department of Art History. He was born in Vancouver, British Columbia on May 23, 1939. He earned his AB at UC Berkeley (1962), and his PhD at the Institute of Fine Arts, New York University (1973). He started teaching at UCLA in 1969 and over the course of his career served as chair of the Department of Art History, interim director for the UCLA Center for Japanese Studies, director of the University of California Tokyo Study Center, Toyota visiting professor at the University of Michigan, Franklin D. Murphy lecturer at the University of Kansas, and Hooker Distinguished Visiting Professor at McMaster University. He was a scholar of Japanese art history and spent seven years doing research and fieldwork in Japan. McCallum retired in 2013 and passed away on October 23, 2013 at the age of 74.
McCallum's research on Japanese art is focused on Japanese Buddhist art and Korean influences. He published three books: Hakuho Sculpture (2012), The Four Great Temples: Buddhist Archaeology, Architecture, and Icons of Seventh-Century Japan (2009), and Zenkoji and its Icon: A Study in Medieval Japanese Religious Art (1994). His interests later included Korean art, modern Japanese art, and tattoos.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes materials related to the academic career and research interests of Professor Donald F. McCallum, who taught courses on Japanese art history at UCLA. The papers includes course materials, lecture notes, syllabi, papers, correspondence for courses on Japanese Buddhist art and Buddhism, Korean art, Japanese sculpture and modern art. Additional materials include talks and presentations delivered by McCallum at various universities and conferences on topics in Japanese art and Buddhism, as well as Korean Buddhist sculpture, and correspondence and drafts of McCallum's published works. Topics covered in this collection include Korean and Japanese art history, Korean Buddhism, Silla-period sculpture, Sui styles, the Tachibana Shrine, Japanese sculpture and architecture, and the Fujiwara-kyo Palace. The digital materials include 11 CDs that contain papers, lectures, course materials, and research.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Course materials, 1968-2012
Series 2: Japanese and Korean art history, 1969-2003
Series 3: Lectures, talks, and symposia, 1971-2013
Series 4: Publications and reviews, 1987-2012
Original order has been maintained.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Buddhist art -- Japan; Decorative arts -- Japan -- History; McCallum, Donald F. (Donald Frederick), 1939-2013 -- Archives; University of California, Los Angeles.Department of Art, Design, and Art History -- Faculty -- Archives
- Series 1: Course materials, 1968-2012
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes materials related to courses and seminars that McCallum taught. Materials include syllabi, exams and answer keys, papers, lecture notes, slides, and correspondence. Course topics include Asuka-dera and Asuka-period sculpture, the Momoyama period, archaeology of the Japanese Islands, Buddhist art, Japanese Buddhism, Korean art, Hakuho sculpture, Yorozu Tetsugoro, Korean Buddhism, Korean Buddhist sculpture, Buddhist art in Japan, Kishida Ryusei, Koga Harue, Japanese ceramics, and Korean influences on Japanese art and Buddhism. Digital materials include 4 CDs that contain courses materials, research, papers, and lectures. Original order has been maintained.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - 114C syllabi and course materials, 2006-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 114C slides for web, 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chinese art survey (115C), 1973-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 114C printed web materials and emails, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 114C assignments (Fall), 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 115C lecture notes and handouts (Winter), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 115C handouts and notes (Winter), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bodiford class materials (Japanese C-260), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Art 115C notes (Spring), circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Art 115C lecture notes (Winter), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 114G course materials and emails, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 114G final exam and slides, 1999-2009 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 115C course materials (Spring), 2002-2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 115C materials on Japanese Buddhism (Spring), 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 114E Korean art, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Korean art course materials, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 115C (Winter), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 115C Korean and Buddhist art history, 1982, 1996-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 115C notes and course materials (Winter), 1987, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 115C art history, 2002-2006 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Course plans, circa 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Courses on Korean and Japanese art, 1983, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Early Korean and Japanese art courses, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 115B: Sui style in Buddhist sculpture, 1973, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 115C: Sesshu and Muromachi painting, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Seminar and bibliography for Japanese gilt-bronze sculptures, 1975, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Yorozu seminar, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Korean Buddhism course materials, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Korean Buddhist sculpture lecture notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Art 260 and 127 course materials (Japanese sculpture), 2001-2011 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Art 127 and 115C course materials, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Syllabus and course materials on Hakuho sculpture, 2003-2012 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Seminar on Soga Clan and early Buddhist art in Japan, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Seminar on Matsumoto Shunsuke, 1986-1987, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Seminar on Shoso-in, circa 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Modern Japanese painting courses (Winter), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Seminar on Modern Japanese art, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Meiji modern art seminar, 1968-1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Art History 260C (Fall), 2006, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Art 260C course materials, 2003, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Course materials on Koga Harue, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Japanese ceramics seminar, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Historiography, circa 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ukiyo-e studies and notes, circa 1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Course bibliography and evaluations, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Departmental and committee correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Senate grant applications, 1994-2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - CDs containing courses materials, research, papers, and lectures, 1998-2012 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    BOX CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
- Series 2: Japanese and Korean art history, 1969-2003
  This series covers research materials, papers, notes, and materials for symposia related to McCallum's academic interests. Topics include Korean art history, Korean Buddhism, Silla-period sculpture, Sui styles, the Tachibana Shrine, Baekje sculpture, Korean reliquaries, Japanese sculpture and architecture (Kamakura, Sui, Tachibana Shrine, and Asuka), the art history of Nara Basin, the Zenjoki Amida Triad, Yorozu Tetsugoro, Matsumoto Shunsuke, and the Fujiwara-kyo Palace. Original order has been maintained.
  - Kamakura sculpture period, circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Washington University Asukadera paper, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Replication of miraculous icons, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Yorozu Tetsugoro, 1974-2001 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Shunsuke Matsumoto ideas, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Shunsuke Matsumoto materials, circa 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Aoki Shigeru and Meiji romance, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ei-kyu paper, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hall: Comments on Mori and Kuno, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hall and McCallum comments on Hakuho, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Fujiwarakyo article and papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Fujiwarakyo lecture and papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fujiwarakyo research, keys to materials, 1998-2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Fujiwarakyo maps, circa 2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Japanese Buddhist paintings, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ryokai mandara, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Japanese Buddhist sculpture (introduction), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Japanese sculpture, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Suibokuga and Bunjinga bibliography, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Murase-Momoyama paintings (including some Sotatus Korin), undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Paper: "Court and Clergy in 7th Century Japan", undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Paper: "Silla and the East Sea" on Korean-Japanese relations, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Review of gilt bronze sculpture at Tokyo National Museum, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Paper: "The Seiryoji Shaka Tradition in Japanese Buddhist Sculpture", undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Korean history, circa 1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Sokkuram's Significance in Korean and Buddhist Art of the 8th Century," Junghee Lee, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Silla sculpture, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Korean influence and early Japan, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sui styles, Silla, and Hakuho, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Tachibana Shriner paper, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Paekche sculpture, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Korean Buddhist sculpture and recent discoveries, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Korean reliquaries, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Kibiike Temple site correspondence and excavation (Tomoko), 1997-1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Lectures, talks, and symposia, 1971-2013
  This series includes lectures, talks, and presentations delivered by McCallum. Materials include lectures and notes on Japanese art and Buddhism, as well as notes for talks delivered at the Detroit Institute of Art, Cleveland Museum of Art, Yale, Stanford, University of Pennsylvania, the Seattle Asian Art Museum, University of Washington, the Japan Society, and LACMA. Lecture topics include Korean Buddhist sculpture, Japanese Buddhism, and modern Japanese painters. Original order has been maintained.
  - Japanese art lectures, 1974-2007 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Silla lecture (Birmingham and Henderson), circa 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Possible talks, circa 1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Santa Barbara Burke lecture, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - LACMA lecture: "The Beginning of Buddhism and Buddhist Art in Japan", undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Lecture tour, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - San Diego talk, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts talk, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art lecture, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Yale conference on Japanese Buddhism, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Stanford talk and "The Ritual Life of Zenkoji", 1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - McMaster lecture: "Ritual Dimensions of the New Year's Ceremonies at Zenkoji", 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - University of Pennsylvania talks, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Seattle lectures on Heian Buddhism and Japanese aesthetic, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - University of Washington Seattle talk, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mokujiki lecture, circa 1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - McMaster conference notes and correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Asian Art Museum of San Francisco talk, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Michele Berton Memorial Lecture on Japanese Art, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art Miroku paper, 2007, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Archaeology lecture materials, 2009 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Japanese archaeology lectures, 2005-2010 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Taiwan paper: "The Japanese Tradition of the Seiryoji Shaka", undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence for Taiwan paper on Seiryoji Shaka, 2009-2010 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - McMaster paper and lecture, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - British Museum symposium on Kamakura sculpture, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - British Museum symposium (Seiryoji), 1991 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Association for Asian Studies conference papers, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Japan Society talk on Hakuho, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Yale and Columbia talks on Shunsuke, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Columbia lecture on Shunsuke, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Asuka Pond lecture, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Koide lecture, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Yorozu lecture and notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Nagoya lecture, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Kishida Ryusei lecture, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Pomona talk on Uemura Shoen and Umehara Ryuzaburo, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Toronto talk: "Japanese Responses to Western Painting in the Pre-War and Post-War Eras", circa 1990 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Japan in Paris lectures, 1987-1988, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Paris in Japan symposium (St. Louis), undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Japan Society talk, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Japanese painting lecture at LACMA, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Japanese decorative arts lecture, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - LACMA lectures, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - County Museum lectures, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Age of the Samurai: Civilization of Medieval Japan" lecture series, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Shin'Enkan collection lecture, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Southern California Japan seminar symposium, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Momoyama painting and lecture notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Toyota professorship talk on Shunsuke, University of Michigan, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Murphy talk on Japanese Hakuho sculpture, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Gakuensi lecture, circa 2008 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - UM Yamadadera lecture, circa 1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Lecture on small gilt-bronze sculpture of early Japan, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Association for Asian Studies meeting presentation, 2013 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Jimbun talk, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - NNM lecture on Sui styles in Korea and Japan, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, 1989, 1994, 2013 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Lecture materials, 1971-1989 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Princeton graduate symposium on East Asian art, 2011-2012 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Symposia correspondence and materials, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Japanese-American symposium, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Archaeology in Japan seminar, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Kishida Ryusei lecture, 2000-2001 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Society for Asian Art lecture, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Kyoto University lecture, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Chonen and Udayana Shaka lecture materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Lectures and other materials, 1998-2008 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Series 4: Publications and reviews, 1987-2012
  This series includes publications and reviews by McCallum. Materials include publishing agreements and contracts, drafts of published works and feedback from readers, permission forms to reproduce images, and correspondence. The majority of the series is related to McCallum's book Hakuho Sculpture (2012). Original order has been maintained.
  - Enku in Antwerp, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Stanford contract, 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - LACMA Buddhist art and images, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Hakuho book (Naomi edited version), 2009-2011 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Permission forms for images, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Permissions for images, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Hakuho Sculpture book, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Image permissions, 2009-2010 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Gakuenoi problem, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Image permissions and invoices, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Horyuji permissions, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Photography rights, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Notes and correspondence on Hakuho Sculpture book, 2012 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Murphy lecture publication, 2001-2008 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Asuka sculpture (new book), undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Hakuho Sculpture book materials, 2003-2006 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Paper: "Enku and Edo Sculptures", circa 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Writings and correspondence for "The Saidiji Lineage of the Seiryoji Shaka Tradition", 1987-1996 (Box 11, Folder 3)